ACT UP, Albany (N.Y.) Chapter; Records apap106
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Act Up Albany (N.Y.) Chapter Records
1983-1992
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Act Up Albany (N.Y.)
apap106
2.47 cubic ft.
This collection details records kept by the ACT UP organization committed to ending the AIDS crisis.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by the Social Justice Center in October 2000.
Administrative History
In March 1987, ACT UP, (AIDS Coalition To Unleash Power), was formed in New York City by a group of people as a diverse, nonpartisan organization of individuals united in anger and committed to ending the AIDS crisis. They wanted to fight back against corporate greed, governmental neglect, and arrogance of the medical community in the 1980s. ACT UP was formed to stop the national and international stigma and discrimination towards people with HIV/AIDS.
ACT UP is a national and international nonpartisan activist group whose mission is to fight for "an end to the AIDS crisis." The goals of ACT UP's direct action include explicit prevention education (such as the distribution of condoms and sex education in schools), information about and access to treatments for AIDS, an end to discrimination against people with HIV/AIDS, including the loss of jobs and benefits, and an "emergency" effort to find a cure for the disease.
Since its inception in March 1987 at the Lesbian and Gay Community Services Center in downtown Manhattan, the AIDS Coalition To Unleash Power grew to thousands of members in more than 70 chapters in the U.S. and worldwide. ACT UP's non-violent direct action, often using vocal demonstrations and dramatic acts of civil disobedience, focuses attention on the crucial issues of the AIDS crisis.
In the late 1980s, ACT UP had many of these demonstrations in front of Wall Street. These included protesting the need for more experimental drugs for AIDS, going into the New York Stock Exchange, and chaining themselves to executive offices. In one instance ACT UP members chained themselves to an executive’s office to lower the price of AIDS drug AZT down from $10,000 per year. This demonstration worked, and a few days later, the drug price was lowered to $6,400 per year.
ACT UP also knew how to use the media to the organization's advantage. Not only were the group's protests written about in The New York Times and other print outlets, but members would also attract television coverage to their protests. On April 15, 1987, members went to the general post office, where people were filling their last-minute tax returns. ACT UP knew that there were usually news reports on people with their late tax returns. This was also where the organization's motto "Silence=Death" was coined. Members showed up with black posters with a pink right side up triangle with the motto on it.
In January 1988, an article was posted in Cosmopolitan magazine by Dr. Robert E. Gould. It said that sexual relations between a man who is HIV positive and a woman was not dangerous. The woman could not get infected even without protection. The women of ACT UP did not want this untrue information to be read. The women meet Dr. Gould and demand an apology and for the article to be taken out of the magazine. When he refused to do so, the women of ACT UP got together to protest Cosmopolitan and what it stood for. The media documented the protest. It brought light to the article and the debate surrounding its accuracy.
On June 17, 1989, the Albany Chapter of ACT UP called for the city to distribute clean needles to drug users and reintroduce and pass a homosexual rights ordinance. In addition, ACT UP, a group whose purpose is to educate American youth about AIDS prevention, opened its first college chapter at the University at Albany, SUNY, in 1990. The Albany Chapter was affiliated with the New York City ACT UP Chapter. A central goal of the group was to educate students and young people about AIDS.
Scope and Contents
The collection documents the activities of ACT UP, Albany New York Chapter, and other chapters from its creation in 1987 to 1992. The collection consists of administrative files such as handbooks for activists, activism in various chapters, the AIDS Curriculum Lesson for the City of Albany, AIDS education and preventive guides and programs, correspondence, minutes, and papers of the Health Systems Agency of Northeastern New York, Inc., from 1990 to 1991. It also includes several legal documents related to human rights, penal law, and public health law, and meeting notes.
Also included in the collection is a videotape, programs and fliers from Albany and other chapters, workshop programs, a boycott fact package, activism related to prisons and AIDS, board of education policies of Massachusetts, New York, and San Francisco. In addition, the collection includes materials from HIV regional forum, numerous news clippings and news releases, draft plan for HIV/AIDS services, and public comments on AIDS. The collection also includes publications about budget funding for AIDS in New York State, reports and research papers, journals, and newsletters published by other organizations.
The strengths of this collection are the posters, fliers, and other activism material from ACT UP chapters. In addition, most of the materials in this collection are in good condition. The collection's lack of administrative records for the Albany chapter is a weakness.
The inactive records of ACT UP/NY were deposited in the New York Public Library in 1996 and the Lesbian Herstory Archives in Brooklyn also hold materials related to ACT UP activities in New York.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1 - Administrative Files, 1989-1992
Series 2 - Subject Files, 1983-1984
Series 3 - Publications, 1988-1992
All series are arranged alphabetically by subject.
Albany, New York; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Medicine and Health Care; Human Sexuality and Gender Identity; Criminal Justice and Prisons; HIV/AIDS awareness; HIV (Viruses); Albany (N.Y.); Videocassettes; Newsletters; Administrative records; Minutes; Programs (documents); ACT UP, ALBANY (N.Y.) CHAPTER
- Administrative Files, 1989-1992; 1; 0.20 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains records about the ACT UP Albany Chapter and other ACT UP chapters' materials dating from 1989 to 1992. It includes a handbook about ACT UP Chapter activism, AIDS education programs and lessons, correspondence and minutes, laws, and meeting notes.
  - A Handbook for Activists, ACT UP, 1991 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 1)
  - Activism, ACT UP Chapters, Maine, New Hampshire, New York, Philadelphia, and Shreveport, 1991-1992 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 2)
  - AIDS Curriculum Lesson, City School District of Albany, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 3)
  - AIDS Education and Preventive Guides and Programs, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Albany Chapter, 1990-1991 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, New York State, 1989-1991 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 6)
  - Draft of Personnel Policies for Regular Employees, Social Justice Center, 1990 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 7)
  - Health Systems Agency of Northeastern New York, Inc., Correspondence, Minutes, and Papers, 1990-1991 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 8)
  - Health Systems Agency of Northeastern New York, Inc., Correspondence, Minutes, and Papers, 1991 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 9)
  - Laws, Human Rights, Penal, and Public Health, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 10)
  - Meeting Notes, Albany Chapter, 1990 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 11)
- Subject Files, 1983-1984; 1987-1991; 2; 0.83 cubic ft.
  This series includes a VHS videotape titled A First Step: AIDS Prevention for Drug Abusers, material related to activism in Albany and other chapters, the annual report of the Albany County Department of Health including budget funding of AIDS programs, Board of Education policies, news clippings and news release from 1986 to 1991, and other materials from across the U.S.
  - A First Step: AIDS Prevention for Drug Abusers, VHS Tape, Undated (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 1)
  - Activism, ACT UP Chapters, Programs and Fliers, 1989-1992; Undated (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 2)
  - Activism, Albany Chapter, Programs, Fliers and Drafts, 1989-1990; Undated (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 3)
  - Activism, Cornell Cooperative Extension Workshop, 1990 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 4)
  - Activism, Miller Brewing Company Boycott Fact Packet, 1990 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 5)
  - Activism, Prisons and AIDS, 1991 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 6)
  - Annual Report of Albany County Department of Health, 1988 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 7)
  - Board of Education Policies, Massachusetts, New York, and San Francisco, 1988; 1990-1991 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 8)
  - Department of Social Services and the AIDS Institute, HIV Enhanced Fees for Physicians Program (HIV-EFD), Undated (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 9)
  - Exhibition of Brothers' Keepers Foundation, Russell Sage College Gallery, 1990 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 10)
  - HIV Regional Forum, State of New York Department of Health, 1991 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 11)
  - News Clippings, 1983-1984; 1987-1991; Undated (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 12)
  - News Release, 1989-1990; Undated (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 13)
  - Plan for HIV/AIDS Services in Northeastern New York, Draft, 1990-1991 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 14)
  - Public Comments on AIDS, Public Forum, 1990 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 15)
  - Activism, Albany Chapter, Posters, Undated (Oversized 1, Folder 1)
  - Activism, Posters and Fliers, Undated (Oversized 1, Folder 2)
- Publications, 1988-1992; 3; 1.44 cubic ft.
  This series documents many reports and publications relating to AIDS published by various organizations. Some of these organizations include the New York State Department of Health, Office of the Attorney General, and the New York African American Institute. Various newsletters and magazine, journals, and handbooks are also included.
  - A Guide to HIV Counseling and Testing, New York State, 1988; 1990; 1991 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 1)
  - Albany County Health Assessment, 1988 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 2)
  - AIDS Directories, New York State, 1990-1991 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 3)
  - AIDS in New York State, New York State Department of Health, 1987-1989 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 4)
  - AIDS New York's Response, 1989 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 5)
  - AIDS Surveillance Monthly Update, New York State, 1990 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 6)
  - AIDS Update, New York State Department of Social Services, Newsletters, 1991 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 7)
  - Budget of New York State, 1990-1991 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 8)
  - Focus on AIDS in New York State, Newsletters, 1990-1991 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 9)
  - Handbooks, 1989-1991 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 10)
  - HIV Regulations 1070 and 1072, New York State Division of Substance Abuse Services, 1989 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 11)
  - Icons and Actions; ACT UP and the Construction of a Nemesis, Research Paper, 1991 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 12)
  - Journals, 1990-1992 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 13)
  - Living with AIDS: United Church of Christ Perspectives, 1988 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 14)
  - Magazines, 1991 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 15)
  - National Commission on AIDS, HIV Disease in Correctional Facilities, Reports, 1991 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 16)
  - Newsletters, 1990-1991 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 17)
  - PWA Support, Newsletters, 1989-1990 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 18)
  - Reports, 1987; 1989-1991; 1983-1992 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 19)
  - Reports, ACT UP, 1991 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 20)
  - Report, Commission on Racial, Ethnic, Religious, and Minority Violence, 1990 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 21)
  - Report, Committee on Children, Youth, and Families, Undated (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 22)
  - Reports, The Coalition for Safe Health Care, 1991 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 23)
  - Report, The VII AIDS Conference Report, Undated (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 24)
  - Research Papers, 1991; Undated (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 25)
  - Gay Community News, Newsletters, 1988-1989 (Oversized 1, Folder 3)
  - Gay Community News, Newsletters, 1990-1991 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 4)
  - Gay Community News, Newsletters, 1991 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 5)